My name is Frank Azaya from Endo State. I was one of the deportees from Libya two days ago.
Before I left, I was staying in River state. I was doing business there.
I was going to Libya, from there to Europe to go and live a better life. As I was going,
on the way, the car we took to Libya - some people died in the car.
We thought that it is a very easy journey.
So on our way we were 34 in number in the car, some people died.
God helped us. He took us to Libya safely.
Along the line, as we were about to cross to Europe, we paid the connection man to take us to Europe.
As were are going, we sailed across the Mediterranean Sea starting from Libya.
On our way, close to international waters the people they call osama -
they came and cut us on top of the sea.
They took us to the underground prison. It's a very hidden place.
Nobody knows that place is existing. A lot of Africans are there - up to 500 people.
They use that place to do business. When they arrest people, they go and sell them to people.
People become bad human beings there. We were there almost four months and some weeks.
In our presence, people were dying there. They gave us one havza in a day.
Morning and evening. We were there and were crying to God.
So one day one Senegalese man came there.
He brought a phone from outside to a brother there.
Just to be clear brother. This underground prison that you were kept in - no one was
allowed to have a phone or any such device in prison, you were just kept there
in that room unable to go out for more than four months.
So as he brought the phone, we collected it.
This is a friend of mine, he said: "Ok, what do we do about the issue now?"
I said: "Let's tell people to come and help us
out of this place here, because nobody knows about that prison in Libya there."
So, as you have heard before, I was talking, calling upon T.B. Joshua,
Adiboye, people in the world to come and help us.That was July 7.
So you recorded this video inside cell within the Libyan prison
which was underground and you were calling on the Nigerian authorities.
You mentioned the names of several prominent men of God asking for help to release you from this prison.
Yes, I did this. Just for two days it was over. In the prison there - they received the video.
They now investigated that I am the one who send the video.
So they came to me. They pointed at me that I am the one who did the video.
They came to me, the man said they will hang me to death.
I was thinking that.....
Just before going ahead, people of God, we can see on the side of the screen
the video in question. Many people who are familiar with social media may have actually watched this video,
as it was spread around the internet showing the condition of the deportees
in Nigeria. He sent it to a friend telling him that they should expose this to the world
for people to know how they are suffering and what they are facing within the confines of
this underground prison. So you said two days after you sent this video -
tell us what happened to you, brother.
Though they now did see the video concerning the prison there. So the owner of the prison
came and investigated concerning the video. People pointed at me that
I am the one who sent the video. The man took me out of the prison.
He said he would sentence me to death.
So they took me to the back yard, they put chain on my neck, so they hung me.
And before I went on the journey, crossing the water, I dreamt about this our
father here T.B. Joshua. I saw him in the dream,
as he was praying for me. So as we were in the prison there, they took me to the back yard.
They went and hung there me with the chain.
In the morning, they thought that I'm dead.
They came and released me. So they took me and threw me
inside the forest. Getting there they found out that I'm still walking.
So they brought me back to prison.
Ok, so we want to understand very clearly. As a punishment for recording this video
you were hung with chains over night until they believed you had died.
They now took your body and took you to the forest.
What did they do when they got to the forest? What was their intention?
They took shovel to dig the ground so that they could bury me there.
They found out that I'm still walking.
You are still breathing.
As they carried you, your body was lifeless, you were limp. They thought you had died.
But as they were about to throw you into the shallow grave, they discovered that you were still breathing.
Yeah. They now brought me back to prison. As I was there, so they locked me
in a single cell in the underground there.
So two days after the men came to me and said that I must pay 10 000 dinars.
to translate to Nigerian money - 500 000 naira.
After four days I told the men that I didn't have that kind of money.
My people in Nigeria could hardly send me the amount of 180 000 naira
that is equal to 10 500 dinars. I paid them saying that this was what I had.
He collected the money. He was still keeping me here.
So after one week interval, ION now intervened in the issue.
As ION now came to the prison, they brought the whole Nigerian people out of the prison,
registered their names so that there were first deportees.
The men locked me inside the room. They said they would not deport me.
Why? Because I'm the one who did the video.
So as they registered those people, even my people here, they now told ION that
somebody inside that room did the video - they would not allow this young man to come out there.
That is how they advanced it for Tripoli.
They now called our embassy in Tripoli there.
So they called the ION people to come back to the prison again
to come and register me. And the next day, they came to the prison.
They told the owner of the prison that embassy is not involved in the issue,
that they should open the gate so that I would be registered.
That's how they brought me out of the prison.
So finally they registered me.The first day I found myself in Nigeria.
I am happy to be here. Actually, I said - let me go to this place to come and share my testimony,
to thank, appreciate the name of God, to come alive, to I appreciate the name of God
for all what God has been using this T.B. Joshua to do for people.
Before I got there, I saw in the dream the way he was acting both spiritually and physically.
That's why I'm here today to come and appreciate the name of God,
appreciating you also, the Lord will bless you in the name of Jesus.
Amen.
Let's just hear a very quick word from the brother beside him who actually took that very video.
Brother, if you introduce yourself and tell us that video you took.
My name is Efemena Amu Steven. I am from Delta State,
I am among the Libyan deportees that were brought to Nigeria from Libya on Thursday.
And I'm also among the prisoners that were being locked up in Osama prison in Libya.
The journey to Libya was horrible and the experience - it was like a horror film.
When we were finally caught in the sea, we were taken to the prison.
We got to discover that the prison is meant for business and not for deportation.
If not for the video that we did, that we sent out, we wouldn't have been here today
because in that video we expose the activities of the prison and that was how almost the whole
of the other African people, from other countries - that was how they got their freedom.
We thank God that the brothers here are out safely. Let's just hear from the other brother as well.
Please, introduce yourself and tell us your own side the story.
Emmanuel! (God is with us! - Matthew 1:23)
My names are Miracle Chidi. I am from Imo State.
My journey to Libya was horrible. I was heading to Europe and not Libya.
But unfortunately, I found myself in Libya after spending years.
On that Mediterranean Sea - we spent three days on top of that sea.
Even when we got to International, we lost souls there.
Osama held us captive there in the sea. We were taken back to Libya.
We thought they were about to deport us, not knowing that it was for a business.
They took us to the prison. We spent months there. People died.
Beatings everyday, no food. No good water. No treatments. I was passing out blood
for weeks in that prison, almost pleading every day, crying and sharing tears just to get just nothing.
Finally, some people born there died. If it was not for the wisdom that was applied for the video,
I don't think we could have come back to Nigeria alive because we lost souls every day.
We give glory to God that our brethren are here, right now we want to listen to another one
of the deportees who will share a slightly different experience concerning what happened
to him when he underwent this horrific journey into Libya.
Brother, please introduce yourself and tell us your own side of this story.
My names are Mr Esosa Odike. I'm from Edo state.
What really happened in my journey? I experienced something that I have never seen in my entire life.
I went to Libya just to cross and we were not there to stay.
but unfortunately, the worst part that I have seen in that journey was on top of the sea, the Mediterranean Sea.
I spent three days on top of the Mediterranean Sea,
when they pushed us because they call it 'lapalapa' - the boat they use,
it's just a polin - the one they use for canopy. They sew it together,
pump it, fill it with gas and air - that is what they put passengers in.
The lowest number of passengers they load on it is 120, 122, 130. That is how they would cross the Mediterranean Sea that has no end.
So we were on top of the Mediterranean Sea...
How many people were in the boat that you were in? How many people?
In my boat we were 122. We spent three days without rescue, the sea
is three colours, white, blue, black. After moving for three days without
getting rescued, so we had to turn back. The heavy wave came and the boat capsized.
But the greatest thing that I saw that gave me joy, when we were in our camp -
before they pushed us, we always prayed and I always watched Emmanuel TV.
in my GoTV at home. And we always prayed in the name of God of Prophet T.B. Joshua.
On top of the sea, I began to call Prophet T.B. Joshua.
But 118 people died in my boat, remaining 4.
So among the 4; I was number 1, my brother that put on the black jacket second,
and 2 other girls. We were the only 4 people that survived among those 122.
So, I didn't even believed I would survive. So when I saw myself in Nigeria,
I didn't believe. Even as I am here, I don't even believe I'm still alive.
Could you share with us, brother - how was it that you were able to survive and what did you see
at that moment that shocked you, when you were in the ocean?
After 2 days, the third day we decided to turn the boat back.
The captain said we should return the boat because there was no rescue.
As we were coming, there was a wave... Automatically, before the wave get to where we were,
I saw people that were dining and wining in the camp,
they began to manipulate, change into vampires,
their teeth began to grow, their fingers began to grow, they began to attack each other.
If anyone bit the other one, the other one would turn to the same thing.
They began to attack themselves. Then I saw that in the midst of humans there were vampires.
I have never seen it in my life before. But on top of the boat I saw people turning to vampires.
Ok, we want to understand very clearly. At the point when the boat was about to capsize -
one of the people inside the boat, you saw them, suddenly as their teeth grew
and they started biting other members within the people on that group on the boat.
And what would happen to the people that they bit?
What happened to the people they bit - assuming, if they bit me,
I would bite another person, that one will bite another person and anybody that they bite
would change and be like them. So immediately, as the boat broke
from the middle - because they put a board on top -
and immediately as the boat broke into two, the lapalapa now covered
So everybody that was sitting in n the center - about 70 to 77 -
immediately all of them fell inside the water.
Yes, all of them fell inside the water. Some of them came up again, they entered the boat.
Instantly, men, women, boys, girls, pregnant women began to manipulate.
Pregnant women that were in that boat were up to about 40. All of them died.
The babies that were up there began to die. I saw vampires, people growing
teeth. They would just bite, as they bit - I am still seeing the picture.
As they bit, the other one would bite the other, the other one would bite the other one.
So I was scared, so I ran back
calling God of Pastor T.B. Joshua. But when I see the miracle of God in the camp
and in the water, especially on the Mediterranean Sea - I believe, I will die in the house of God.
So our brother is re-narrating his experience what he saw with his own eyes,
when he was on the top of the ocean, as his boat capsized. This is not
a horror film or something that he just imagined. This was his own experience
as people were dying in his midst. Brother, how did you actually survive? What did you do?
How did you manage to survive, when all the of the 90% of your colleagues drowned?
On top of the boat, after 3 days, after we saw people on top of the sea - they looked like birds.
Dead bodies - the water began to float them, so I kept holding the boat because on that boat
there was a rope that they put round the boat, that rope lead to the general valve.
So I held the rope and we were still calling the God of Pastor T.B. Joshua. I held the boat
without no shirt. I was with just a knicker. I was not with a life jacket,
I was on top of the boat. On the third day, a ship came.
Those Chinese people were inside.
So they took us to the ship. So they promised that they would give us shelter, they would take us to their place.
But when we were sleeping, then we saw some policemen putting on soldier uniform.
So they were Libyans. They woke us up, and they took me and my friend and the other two girls
back to Libya. That is how we have been imprisoned till Thursday morning,
when they brought us out and deported us.
Let's hear from the other gentleman who was also a survivor on this boat.
As we listen, we say that there was 120 plus people in the boat and only 4 survived,
two of them are in our midst. So brother, can you share briefly your own side of this experience.
My names are Iboye Ufuoma. I am from Delta state.
The worsest thing I have ever experienced in my life was is encountering on that route to Libya.
I have not seen a thing like this before.
But the most worseful one is in the sea.
Likewise my brother have said, that was the worsest experience.
We were 122 in the boat. We were seeking asylum abroad,
to make sure we can survive. So as we approached, we've been in the sea for 3 days.
At the end of the day, a mighty wave came and smashed our boat and the boat teared into two.
Out of that boat, inside the boat, everybody in the middle sank inside the water.
So it was remaining only four of us, and out of the four - two were women, the other two were boys.
So I have been in that water; all my legs were eaten up by fishes. Fish were eating my legs.
And do you know my body was...I don't know because the salty water was eating up all my body,
and there were fish feeding under my leg. So a thought came to me because when we were in the camp,
we were always using the God of T.B. Joshua to pray.
The mind came to me and said - why don't you shout the name of God of T.B. Joshua,
if all those things that are growing up here". Because I finally noticed that there were people manifesting
a kind of things I have never experienced before. People were growing up teeth.
Everyone that fell inside the water, when he came out - he came out with another shape.
They were growing up teeth, growing up fingers. They were biting the one inside the boat again.
So everywhere was just scattered.
Brother, you know people, it's difficult for people to believe what you are saying
because it's a strange thing. You mean, that when people were drowning, as they entered the water
that very same person, when they came back - you would see their features have changed?
Their teeth had grown, they had grown claws and they became very wild
and aggressive. Is this what you yourself saw with your eyes on this sea?
That was exactly what I experienced. People were growing up teeth.
The people we were meeting with inside the boat were growing up teeth again
to eat up the people inside the boat. That was how the boat finally capsized.
After the boat capsized, it was remaining only four of us.
This my brother here; and some other two women.
Those ones have gone to their various places.
So it was terrible, so terrible that I have not seen in my life but I have witnessed it.
But to the glory of God you survived. You said, even your skin changed colour because
of the salt in the water.
My skin totally changed because the water is salty water.
It eats up my body. And the fishes were feeding under my legs. So immediately I called on the name of
the God of T.B. Joshua, the next day we saw a ship that came from nowhere
that rescued us. Inside the ship they were white men from China.
After they finished the rescue, they said we shouldn't worry,
that they would give us shelter, they would make us ok, that they would handle us to their country
and take good care of us.
In the night, when we were sleeping, suddenly we saw some people putting on military uniform.
They came to wake us up. To my greatest surprise I said: "What is this?
You people promised us that you will take us to their place. So what am I seeing?"
They said we should get up in Libyan language. They said: "Asma, tahala!"
I said: "What on earth is tahala?"
So what our brother is explaining is that even after suffering in such a condition
seeing, witnessing his own colleagues drowning before his eyes, some of them even transforming
into demonic figures, as a result of that death -
even after that way he survived, he was still taken back to Lybia into captivity.
So the effort all the years and months he spent going abroad in attempt to reach Europe -
he never even reached the destination he tried to get to.
He went back to Lybia and back to the prison.
And that was how you finally were deported back to Nigeria with your colleagues two days ago.
Is that right?
Yes, that was how I finally deported here to Nigeria and I had spent a lot of months in the prison.
Eating havza daily.
Let's just hear from the other young man there to quickly conclude the experiences
of our brothers. Brother, just introduce yourself to us and tell us what happened to you when you were in Libya.
My name is Mathias Edegbe. I am from Eboni state, Abakaliki Town.
I went to Libya last year April. As I went to Lybia, I went to cross to Europe.
We reached the Mediterranean Sea. They arrested us, they took us back to dry land.
As we were coming back to dry land, the boat capsized.
People died. So they called rescue. Some people were rescued and did go back to dry land.
So I was trying to escape from them. The street boys catched me and put back
to the prison. As I was trying to pray that day, it was around 12 o'clock in the night.
The Arab man came, he said: "What is happening, why are you making noise inside the prison?"
I told him that I wanted to pray. That is how he brought gun and started to shoot inside the house.
Many people died. He held me and used bottle and knife
and cut my hand. Look at my hand. My teeth almost came out of my mouth.
They used gun and broke my head. I received some injuries inside my body,
as we are talking just now. So that one passed.
This year I still tried to cross to Europe.
So brother, the scars we are seeing on your arms are wounds that were inflicted
upon you in the Libyan prison, when they told you to stop making noise
during your prayer. They used a glass to open and tear skin on your arm
and even displaced the bone in your arm. Is that right?
So what we are seeing - is the bone coming out, sir?
This is the bone. They beat me and used knife, bottle and cut my hand.
So this year, I went to cross again. Almost the same thing that happened last year - that's how it happened.
And that is how you were deported back to Nigeria with your colleagues?
Ok, let's finally hear from the lady at the far end who actually came with a very small child.
Libya Deportees Share Life Experiences
Can you introduce yourself to us and tell us your own experiences in Libya.
My name is Ada. I stayed in Nigeria, before one of my friends from Germany
said I should come. So I reached Saba, where the guy came to pick me up.
So I went to see the connection man to help me to find work.
When I got there, I worked for two months.
The woman came and she beat me. As she beat me. She asked me to bring a cup
and I brought plate because these words are related in Arabic.
So she beat me. There they are used to stay on ground not mopping.
They use something else.
So as I cleaned and finished - no food.
Instead of telling me to remove the tea cup,
she started beating me again.
I said I better run away from the big person like that.
Ok, so for the benefit of those who may not understand what our sister is explaining.
She is speaking in Pidgin English. She is explaining how she was among the people that
travelled illegally through the deserts to Libya
and upon arriving she was actually sold into slavery, where she was forced
to work under a particular lady who maltreated her, beat her mercilessly.
Even she was so confused, as a result of the beating that if she was asked to bring
something, she would bring the wrong thing which could lead to a lot of beating
and torture and she asked herself, is this what she travelled from Nigeria for,
to work, as a slave. So can you tell us, sister, how did you now end up in prison?
And what led to you being here with this little baby?
As I went around on the road, I met one boy on the road.
I said I needed help. He couldn't help me. I said: "Help me, put me in a house."
From there he gave me belly. He still
couldn't help me.
She's explaining that she ran away from this particular lady and on the street,
she met some man who promised to help her. The man took her to his house and that man
impregnated her. So tell us, what happened after that, after you became pregnant for this man.
We couldn't go for pushing, they couldn't push us to go sea side - that is where we
went to cross to Europe. And I was pregnant.
So from there we could see a plane.
We believed this was the plane where they would direct us - Italian plane.
Arab men drove the boat. So we couldn't go the wrong side.
But here now water got spoiled. People even said last prayer. They didn't even finish.
Some stayed at this edge, and some stayed at this edge, as the waters slapped.
People fell in the water and entered inside the boat. I thiught I would die in this sea.
God brought a rescue - Libyan rescue.
So they rescued us. As they rescued us, we were imprisoned for 2 months.
I got confused.
Okay, so just to explain what our sister is saying. With this man that impregnated her
they attempted to travel on the sea to Europe through entering the rubber dinghy,
known as lapalapa - a very small boat, inflatable boat.
As they were going across the Mediterranean Sea, while she was pregnant,
although they saw a plane above which they believed was a signal that they would be rescued -
at that point, storm set in and people at the extreme end of the boat, began to fall into the water.
They died by drowning and then finally a boat came to rescue them
but they discovered that it was a Libyan boat who took them back to Libya,
and took them to prison. So whilst there in prison, tell us what happened there.
When we were in the prison, they wanted to escape.
As the guy who gave me child - before he ran, he said he was going to give me number,
so that I could locate him. He did not give me, I did not see him that night when they all escaped.
Before I knew, the car left. Now on one of them came to meet me saying: "That boy ran away,
left you here. What will you do now?" I said I did not know what to do
because he didn't give me his number. So I didn't hear from him for almost
two months now.
So I don't even know how to locate them.
Our sister is explaining that whilst they were in prison, the owner of the pregnancy,
her boyfriend burst out of the prison, escaped with several others inmates.
He told her to follow, but because she was heavily pregnant
she could not. And even before he left, he had not given her contact details of his family.
So there was no trace of him. She doesn't know now whether he's alive or dead.
She doesn't know the number or name of any of his family members and to this point
since he ran away from the prison, she has no idea of his whereabouts.
Mrs Ada & Baby
Libya Deportee Life Experience
So we are seeing our sister overcome by emotion. We can imagine what it means
for the father of her child to have disappeared and she has no ways of tracing or knowing the family
or even whether he's alive or dead right now.
And we can understand what our sister is passing through, the reason why she is crying.
Tell us, the baby you are holding...
So inside the prison, nobody to help. I got to call one Yoruba girl to help me.
She held me, she used granite soil to rub my vagina, to rub my back.
The baby's head didn't come outside. I pushed inside the prison there.
So as God may have it, that's how I gave birth to my baby.
No treatment, nothing. Even my belly is still big
because the blood from inside did not come outside.
Now I came here...
Okay, people of God, we are listening to our sister. A question, sister.
How old is this baby you are holding right now?
A week and three days.
So we're hearing from our sister the baby is just one week and three days old.
She delivered the baby in the Libyan prison
without any medical assistance with just the prisoners who were around
who helped her to push. One week after that, she was among those who were deported to Nigeria.
She has no way of knowing, where the father of this child is or contacting his family
and that's why she's among those that came to the Synagogue, Church Of All Nations
to seek supports and help. Now, people of God, we know that at The Synagogue, Church of All Nations
we have been regularly taking care of those who are deported from Libya -
Nigerians deported from Libya. Individuals who are before us are among the people
who arrived - nearly 100 - they arrived from Libya and they came
directly to the SCOAN to seek supports.
So once again, Prophet T.B. Joshua supported that group with 2.4 million naira
to help them go back to their various states, take care of them, give food and
enable them to start their lives back in Nigeria with something
as a result of their terrible traumatic experiences abroad.
This is not the first time. Regular viewers of Emmanuel TV will know that Prophet T.B. Joshua
has with the support of Emmanuel TV Partners has been regularly
taking care of Nigerians deported from Libya and this set is just one of many
who have visited the SCOAN. Right now, for the people who are here in our midst
Prophet T.B. Joshua said for the seven who are here right now,
we are here to present to you the sum of 1 million naira.
This is the sum of 1 million naira for the seven who are here in our midst,
to support each and every single one of you to start a new life in Christ Jesus,
to care for our mother here with a little child, when with making God's Word the standard for your lives.
So once again, this is 1 million naira for the seven deportees who are here
to enable them to start their lives afresh in Christ Jesus.
Let's put our hands together for Jesus Christ!
Libya Deportees Receive 1 Million Naira From Prophet T.B. Joshua And Emmanuel TV Partners
Thank God for what God has done for us today - mother, help me thank God.
Libya Deportees Receive 1 Million Naira From Prophet T.B. Joshua and Emmanuel TV Partners
On behalf of Prophet TB Joshua and the Emmanuel TV partners
this group of Libya deportees will receive over 1 million naira to support them and
for their new life in Christ Jesus, so each and every one of the men will receive
one hundred and fifty thousand naira each and the mother with her child
will receive 200 hundred thousand naira.
My name is Mr. Osousa Odgeye. I appreciate so much what the man of God have done in my life
because all the years and the debt I have passed through in the land of Libya -
within the twinkle of an eye, he wiped them away, he gave my life a meaning.
I was given 150,000 naira to start a new life.
May God continually bless him for his wonderful work in my life.
My name is Frank Azeya from Edo state, deportee from Lybia.
I came with empty hands. I cried to T.B. Joshua and he wiped away my tears.
With my colleagues, we came here, he gave us an amount of 1,30 million naira.
Each person received an amount of 150 thousand naira to start a new life.
We don't know how to thank you. We think the Lord will reward you.
The Lord will bless you. I and my colleagues here - we so much appreciate you.
Thank you very much, sir.
Libya Deportees Receive 1 Million Naira From Prophet T.B. Joshua and Emmanuel TV Partners
TT: Monica Asefa 29/10/18
RV: Pavel Tatyana Zheleznyakov 25/11/2018